Philip Hauge Abelson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Philip Hauge Abelson Papers1939-2002 (bulk 1970-1989)
MSS84803
Abelson, Philip Hauge
16,100 items 46 containers 18.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Nuclear physicist, chemist, and editor. Correspondence, notes, reports, speeches and writings, and other papers documenting Abelson's contribution to scientific policy-making through committees, organizations, and publications.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Abelson, Philip Hauge.
Organizations
American Association for the Advancement of Science.; American Geophysical Union.; Bio-energy Council.; Carnegie Institution of Washington.; International Union of Geological Sciences.; Jet Propulsion Laboratory (U.S.); National Academy of Sciences (U.S.)
Subjects
Science--Societies, etc.; Science.
Titles
Science.
Occupations
Chemists.; Editors.; Nuclear physicists.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Philip Hauge Abelson, nuclear physicist, chemist, and editor, were given to the Library of Congress by Abelson in 2001 and 2002.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Philip Hauge Abelson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1913, Apr. 27 Born, Tacoma, Wash.
1935 M.S., Washington State University, Pullman, Wash.
1936 Married Neva Martin (died 2000)
1939 Ph.D., University of California, Berkeley, Calif. Identified products of uranium fission
1940 Codiscoverer with Edwin M. McMillan of Element 93 (Neptunium)
1941-1945 Associate physicist, physicist, senior physicist, and principal physicist, Naval Research Laboratory, Washington, D.C.
1945 Awarded U.S. Navy Distinguished Civilian Service Medal
1946-1953 Chairman, Biophysics Section, Department of Terrestrial Magnetism, Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, D.C.
1953-1971 Director, Geophysics Laboratory, Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, D.C.
1959 Elected to National Academy of Sciences
1960-1963 General Advisory Committee, Atomic Energy Commission
1962-1984 Editor, Science magazine
1968-1981 Council member, National Academy of Sciences, with a seven-year absence from 1971 to 1978
1971-1978 President and trustee, Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, D.C.
1972 Awarded Kalinga Prize, UNESCO
1978-1980 Chairman, Board of Trustees, Bio-Energy Council
1984 Received Distinguished Public Service Award, National Science Foundation
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Philip Hauge Abelson (1913- ) span the years 1939-2002, with the bulk of the material dating from 1970 to 1989. The papers are organized in the following series: Committees and Organizations, Science Magazine, Speeches and Writings, and a Miscellany consisting of awards, biographical material, general correspondence, photographs, and printed material.
The Committees and Organizations series contains correspondence, financial records, grant proposals, minutes, publications, and reports relating to Abelson's participation in scientific professional organizations and advisory committees. Notable organizations include the American Geophysical Union, Bio-Energy Council, Carnegie Institution of Washington, International Union of Geological Sciences, Jet Propulsion Laboratory at the California Institute of Technology, and the National Academy of Sciences.
The Science Magazine series consists of texts of editorials written by Abelson during his tenure as editor of the chief publication of the American Association for the Advancement of Science. An index to the editorials is included. The correspondence primarily contains reactions of the general public and the scientific community to opinions voiced by Abelson in his editorials. As editor of this important publication, Abelson visited both foreign and domestic research laboratories. His notes and correspondence regarding these trips are included.
The Speeches and Writings series contains chiefly texts of speeches given by Abelson to educational institutions, private companies, and scientific organizations. Also included are articles written for publications other than Science and correspondence regarding two of Abelson's books.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in four series:
Committees and Organizations, 1946-2001
Science Magazine, 1962-2000
Speeches and Writings, 1950-1999
Miscellany, 1939-2002
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm2001084803
Container List
- Committees and Organizations, 1946-2001 (Box 1-24)
  Correspondence, financial records, grant proposals, minutes, publications, and reports relating to Abelson's participation in scientific professional organizations and advisory committees.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of committee or organization and therein chronologically.
  - Ad Hoc Geological Committee on Remote Sensing from Space, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee, American University, Washington, D.C., 1973
  - Advisory Panel on the Documentation, Dissemination, and Use of Research and Development Results, 1963-1964, undated
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1965-1966, 1972-1979, 1990, (4 folders)
  - American Chemical Manufacturers Association, 1980
  - American Council on Education, 1978
  - American Geophysical Union
    - 1973-1979
    - 1980-1983, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1973-1979
  - Bio-Energy Council
    - Correspondence
      - 1977
      - 1978-1979, (7 folders) (Box 3)
    - Financial records, 1978-1980, undated
    - Grant proposals, 1979-1980, undated, (7 folders) (Box 4)
    - Meeting minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Miscellany, 1979-1980, undated
  - Brookings Institution, Washington, D.C., 1964-1966, 1977-1983
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, D.C.
    - Correspondence, 1967-1970, 1980-1982
    - News releases and printed matter, 1962-1963, undated
    - Reports
      - Director of the Department of Terrestrial Magnetism, 1946-1954, (2 folders)
      - Director of the Geophysical Laboratory
        - 1953-1963, (2 folders)
        - 1963-1969, (6 folders) (Box 6)
        - 1969-1971, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - General Electric Corporate Research and Development, 1977-1978, undated, (4 folders)
      - President
        - 1946, 1956-1961
        - 1964-1977, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Specialized Conference on the Application of Science and Technology to Latin American Development, Brasilia, Brazil, 1972, (3 folders)
    - Studies of Biosynthesis in Escherichia Coli, 1963 (Box 9)
  - Chemical Abstracts Service, 1976-1980
  - Chemical Industry Institute of Toxicology, Research Triangle Park, N.C., 1979, 1985
  - Council on Science and Technology for Development
    - 1977-1979, (5 folders)
    - 1980-1981, undated (Box 10)
  - Encyclopedia of Bioethics, 1973-1974
  - Energy Information Administration, 1979
  - Geological Survey of Canada, 1979
  - International Geological Correlation Program, 1978-1981
  - International Union of Geological Sciences
    - 1972-1979, (3 folders)
    - 1980
      - Jan.-Mar.
      - Apr.-Nov., (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, Calif.
    - Correspondence, 1976-1984, (3 folders)
    - Notes, 2001
    - Photographs, 1978-1980
    - Printed matter
      - 1978-1980
      - 1981, undated (Box 12)
  - National Academy of Public Administration, 1978-1984, (4 folders)
  - National Academy of Sciences
    - Awards, 1981-1982
    - Committee on an Aging Society, 1982-1983
    - Committee to Review the Office of Information, 1982
    - Congressional endowment proposal, 1980
    - Correspondence
      - 1978
      - 1979-1980, (7 folders) (Box 13)
      - 1981-1984, (4 folders) (Box 14)
    - Finance Committee, 1974-1979
    - Geology Section, 1979-1983, (2 folders)
    - Institute of Medicine, 1973-1982
    - Meeting minutes
      - 1978
      - 1979-1981, (6 folders) (Box 15)
    - National Research Council
      - Advisory Committee on International Investment, Technology, and Development
        - 1980
        - 1981-1983 (Box 16)
      - Biomass Substitutes for Liquid Fuels Symposium, Campinas, Brazil, 1981-1982, (2 folders)
      - Climate Research Board, 1980-1984, (3 folders)
      - Commission on International Relations, 1976-1981 (Box 17)
      - Commission on Natural Resources
        - Board on Mineral and Energy Resources, 1975-1980, (4 folders)
        - Miscellany, 1979
      - Committee on Abiogenic Methane, 1979, (2 folders) (Box 18)
      - Committee on Geology, 1979
      - Committee on Internal Management Structure, 1981-1982
      - Committee on International Human Resources Issues, 1979
      - Division of Earth Sciences, 1973-1975
      - Division of Medical Sciences
        - Committee on Radiation Cataracts, 1949-1955
        - Subcommittee on Shock, 1950-1953, (2 folders)
      - Geological Sciences Board, 1979-1983, undated
      - Geophysics Research Board
        - 1973-1978
        - 1979, (6 folders) (Box 19)
        - 1980-1984, undated, (8 folders) (Box 20)
      - Governing Board meeting, 1979, (2 folders) (Box 21)
      - Miscellany, 1973, 1979
      - U.S. National Committee for the International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics, 1973-1974, 1981-1983
    - Printed matter, 1978-1983, (3 folders)
    - Treasurer's reports, 1979-1981
  - National Association of Science Writers, 1963, 1976-1978
  - National Commission on Air Quality, 1981
  - National Science Foundation, 1964-1966, 1973-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1979-1982, undated
  - President's Science Advisory Committee, 1980
  - Sigma Xi, 1964, 1973, 1979-1981, undated, (5 folders)
  - Strategic Arms Limitations Talks (SALT), 1979
  - United States Association for the Club of Rome
    - 1977
  - United States Association for the Club of Rome (Box 23)
    - 1978-1981, (5 folders)
  - United States Congress, Office of Technology Assessment, 1978-1979
  - United States Geological Survey, 1979-1984, (2 folders)
  - United States Navy, Naval Research Laboratory, Washington, D.C. (Box 24)
    - Atomic Energy Submarine, 1946
    - Liquid Thermal Diffusion, 1946, 1958, 1985-1998, (4 folders)
  - Washington Gas Light Co., 1974-1975, 1981-1984
- Science Magazine, 1962-2000 (Box 25-36)
  Texts of editorials written by Abelson, correspondence in reaction to his editorials, and notes taken on business trips.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Correspondence (Box 25)
    - 1962, (2 folders)
    - 1963
      - Jan.-Aug., (6 folders)
      - Sept.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1964-1965, (6 folders)
    - 1966-1969, (8 folders) (Box 27)
    - 1970-1972, (9 folders) (Box 28)
    - 1973-1974, (8 folders) (Box 29)
    - 1975-1985, undated, (8 folders) (Box 30)
  - Editorials (Box 31)
    - Index, 1962-2000, (2 folders)
    - 1962-1971, (7 folders)
    - 1972-1973, (7 folders) (Box 32)
    - 1974-1987, (7 folders) (Box 33)
    - 1988-2000, (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Trips
    - California, 1962
    - China, 1978-1979, (2 folders)
    - India and Thailand, 1984, (3 folders) (Box 35)
    - London, England, 1963-1964
    - Research laboratories
      - Bell Laboratories, 1964, 1979
      - E.I. DuPont de Nemours and Co., 1978, undated
      - Exxon Research and Engineering Co., 1978
      - General Electric Co., 1975-1978
      - General Motors Research Laboratories, 1977-1979
      - International Business Machines Corp., 1978
      - Miscellany, 1978-1983, undated
      - Texas Instruments, 1978 (Box 36)
      - 3M Co., 1979
- Speeches and Writings, 1950-1999 (Box 36-42)
  Articles, books, and texts of speeches along with related correspondence and administrative material.
  - Articles (Box 36)
    - 1950-1992, (7 folders)
    - 1993-1999, undated, (2 folders) (Box 37)
  - Books
    - Energy: Uses, Conservation, and Supply, 1974
    - Enough of Pessimism, 1985-1987, 1993-1998, undated
  - Speech file
    - 1963-1964, (4 folders)
    - 1965-1973, (9 folders) (Box 38)
    - 1974-1979, (7 folders) (Box 39)
    - 1980-1981, (6 folders) (Box 40)
    - 1982
      - Jan.-May
      - July-Nov., (4 folders) (Box 41)
    - 1983-1990, (4 folders)
    - 1991-1999, undated, (3 folders) (Box 42)
- Miscellany, 1939-2002 (Box 42-46)
  Awards, biographical material, general correspondence consisting primarily of invitations to speak, photographs, and printed matter.
  - Abelson, Neva, 1991-2000, undated (Box 42)
  - Appointment books and calendars, 1963-1979, (5 folders)
  - Awards and honors, 1962-1963, 1974-1995 (Box 43)
  - Biographical material
    - Autobiography, 1997, undated
    - Miscellany, 1962-1965, 1972-1985, undated
    - Oral history transcripts, 2002, undated
  - Correspondence
    - 1962-1970, (6 folders)
    - 1971-1976, (10 folders) (Box 44)
    - 1977
      - Jan.-Sept., (2 folders)
      - Oct.-Dec. (Box 45)
    - 1978-1981, (6 folders)
    - 1983
      - Jan.-Apr., (2 folders)
      - May-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 46)
    - 1984-1991, 1997, undated, (3 folders)
  - Photographs, 1939, 1968, 1984, undated
  - Printed matter, 1961-1975, 1982, undated, (2 folders)